Well, as it turned out, American culture
too got in on the mass production craze
of the post-World War II years, and
that, my dear pupil, is a saucy tale.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked conformity style, let's get
to it. So, hopefully that brain folder
in which you crammed all the content for
unit seven is still online, and if so,
you'll no doubt remember that this is
not the first time we've talked about
the spread of mass culture in the United
States. So, recall that during the 1920s
and 30s, the radio and cinema were
mainly responsible for thrusting a
national culture onto Americans, and
that was kind of a big deal. You see,
previously regional culture was a far
stronger influence on local society
since Americans learned their cultural
traits like how to speak and what to
believe and how to vote, etc., from
other people in their local environment.
But, the growing influence of mass media
presented people with a more national
American culture rather than a
distinctly regional culture. Even so,
the spread of mass culture in the 20s
and 30s also did highlight regional
cultures by presenting programs like the
Grand Ole Opry or artists that belonged
to the Harlem Renaissance, which meant
that Americans were also exposed to
cultural traits that were different from
theirs. However, in the years after
World War II, the widespread adoption of
the television meant that mass culture
was becoming increasingly homogeneous,
which is a nasty, hairy word that you
might not know, but will almost
certainly show up on your exam. So, let
me explain it up real quick. So,
homogeneous by definition means that
multiple parts of something are the same
or similar. Like, homo means same and
genius means kind, so it's related to
the word genetic. So, the spread of mass
culture in the post-war years meant that
all the various groups of Americans who
were increasingly consuming mass culture
through the television were becoming
more and more similar to each other. And
so, it wasn't for nothing that this
period got itself the moniker the Age of
Conformity. Oh, and by the way, if you
want to know guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos, then get
that clicky finger out and check that
link in the description. Anyway, we also
need to briefly consider how television
actually spread all this mass culture
that I've been flapping my mouth hole
about. So, in those days, three major
networks, namely CBS, NBC, and ABC,
presented television programming that
appealed to the mainstream majority of
Americans. For example, shows like I
Love Lucy and Leave It to Beaver
presented absolute moral values and
portrayed an idealized version of the
American nuclear family. On Leave It to
Beaver, Americans tuned in to witness
the happiness and contentment of a nigh
on two perfect middle-class nuclear
suburban family. Like the mother was
altogether domestic and seemed to
delight in just doing the dishes and
raising her children all in her lovely
dress and pearls. And the father worked
to pay the bills and was keen on
teaching his children lessons about the
value of conformity and responsibility.
And then other shows like I Love Lucy
were equally popular but gave a slightly
more complex narrative offering. The
protagonist was also a domestic woman
but she had dreams of becoming an
entertainer. And while the show is in
part a chronicle of her failed attempts
to make it in that world, it still
challenged the pressure to conform to
assigned gender roles even if the
challenge was only occasional. But then
religion, too, got the mass conformity
treatment in the post-war years as well.
Now, remember that all of this is going
on during the Cold War. No small part of
that struggle was the ideological battle
between the democratic capitalism of the
United States and the authoritarian
communism of the Soviet Union. And it
soon became clear to American culture
makers that one chief way to distinguish
Americans from Soviets was by
emphasizing that while the Soviets were
godless atheists, Americans were godly
Christians. And to be clear, plenty of
Soviets were believers and a significant
portion of them were Christians. But
since the Soviet state pursued a program
of religious suppression and advocated
loyalty to the state above all else,
American policy makers just tried to
make things as simple as possible for
Americans. Soviets were dumb atheists
and Americans were righteous Christians.
Full stop. No equivocation. To that end,
Congress added the phrase under God to
the pledge of allegiance in 1954 and
officially adopted a new motto for the
United States, In God We Trust.
Furthermore, television also contributed
to the mass homogenization of American
religion and there's no better example
here than the nationally broadcast
revivals led by Protestant evangelist
Billy Graham. His sermons melded
biblical teaching with conservative
politics and a strong anti-communist
message. And while he would have said
that his goal was to convert lost
Americans to a simple Christianity,
there was also a powerful, often
unspoken subtext, namely that to be a
Christian was to be opposed to
communism. And so in that way it was
sometimes difficult to discern where
being a Christian stopped and being an
American began. But anyway, Graham and
folks like him and to the growth of a
distinct form of Protestantism, known as
Evangelicalism, which shared many core
commitments with the fundamentalist
movement that we talked about in the
1920s. Now, I could go on multiplying
examples of the homogenization of mass
culture, but now it's time for me to
tell you about four groups who railed
against this conformity and took steps
to challenge it. First of all, artists
challenged the conformity of the age,
and there's no better example here than
the Beat Generation. So, they were a
group of poets and writers who used
their talents to expose the underlying
rot that accompanied white middle-class
culture that was being peddled by
television. For example, Jack Kerouac's
novel On the Road praised the freedom
that came with travel and exploration
that served as an escape from the
drudgery of the typical middle-class
lifestyle. Additionally, Kerouac's
characters used drugs and alcohol, and
not secretly and in shame, but gleefully
as a means to finding unique and
meaningful life experiences. And many
artists in the Beat Generation were
drawn far more to black culture both for
the freshness of their musical forms and
the uniqueness of their standards of
beauty. And though he was not considered
a member of the Beat Generation, a 1950s
novelist that dealt with similar themes
was J.D. Salinger. In The Catcher in the
Rye, his protagonist Holden Caulfield
spends his young life railing against
the phoniness and conformity of mass
culture, and in the end is committed to
a sanatorium for the mentally insane.
Man, it's a real heartwarmer. Okay, now
the second group that challenged the
conformity of the age was intellectuals.
So, if the Beat Generation used their
feely-feely parts to rebel, these folks
used their thinky-thinky parts. For
example, a significant ingredient in the
1950s spread of mass culture was the
emphasis on consumerism and holding an
unquestioning faith in the goodness of
corporate capitalism. And look, all you
had to do was look at the massive wave
of suburbanization and the wealth that
accompanied it to come to the conclusion
that the system was in fact working and
therefore ought to be embraced. However,
some intellectuals like economist John
Kenneth Galbraith thought this was about
the dumbest thing he'd ever heard. In
his 1958 book, The Affluent Society,
Galbraith acknowledged that the post-war
economy had indeed created enormous
private wealth, but at the expense of
public goods like schools and parks and
libraries, et cetera. Additionally, he
sharply criticized the machine of mass
consumption by arguing that not only did
the advertising industry artificially
create a demand for mass-produced goods,
but Americans themselves were being
conditioned by this whole system to
equate consumption with happiness. And
in the third group raising a challenge
to cultural conformity was homosexuals.
So, in a time when mass culture promoted
heterosexuality as the only norm to be
embraced, some homosexual activists in
opposition to laws that criminalized
their orientation sought to challenge
those conclusions. For example, in 1951,
a group of gay men founded the
Mattachine Society to advocate for gay
rights. And then a few years later, a
similar organization focused on lesbian
rights was founded, namely the Daughters
of Bilitis. work of these organizations
and others like them laid the foundation
for a more focal and widespread gay
rights movement that began in the 1960s.
And finally, the fourth group raising an
absolute ruckus over conformity was all
kinds of rebellious youth, specifically
teenagers. Now, here's where I tell you
that teenagers have only existed for
about 70 years. I see that question mark
growing over your head, so let me
explain. So, in the post-war years, high
school attendance skyrocketed, and that
led to the first scholarly definition of
a new age group in American culture, the
teenager. And this distinct group of
young Americans began to distinguish
themselves from their conformity-minded
parents in many ways, but for sure the
most vocal way was their embrace of rock
and roll music. This music was
positively scandalous to the older folk
who clutched their pearls and said to
their kids, "Son, if Frank Sinatra is
good enough for Jesus, he's good enough
for you." Anyway, rock and roll music
was a style of music pioneered by black
artists like Chuck Berry, but it entered
the mainstream through a massively
popular white artist, namely Elvis
Presley. And he combined his own style
with black rhythm and blues and became
massively popular, again thanks to the
television. And parents were horrified
when Elvis showed up on their TVs
gyrating his hips and dancing in a
sexually suggestive manner, but those
rascally teenagers flat-out loved it,
and that was no small part of their
reaction against their parents' push for
cultural conformity. Okay, you can click
here to watch my other Unit 8 videos, or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brainfolds. I'm glad
you came around, and I'll catch you on
the flip-flop. I'm Larrabee out.